<chapter label="3" id="canvas-chapter">
<title>The Canvas</title>
 <sect1 id="canvas">
  <title>Canvas Introduction</title>
   <para>
    The canvas is the main part of Dia.  The Dia canvas is the window where all
    the user's objects will be placed on the screen and arranged.  When the
    diagram is printed or saved, the contents of the canvas will be saved.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gridlines">
  <title>Grid Lines</title>
   <para>
    Grid lines are similar to the lines on graph paper.  They allow the user
    to easily align objects on the canvas.  The grid lines can be temporarily 
    hidden for the current document choosing the menus item 
    <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>
      View
     </guimenu>
     <guimenuitem>
      Show Grid
     </guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
    The grid lines can be turned hidden for all new documents by going into
    <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>
      File
     </guimenu>
     <guimenuitem>
      Preferences
     </guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
    In the Grid Lines tab, click the checkbox labelled Visible and leave it 
    empty to hide the grid lines.  
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="Rulers">
  <title>Rulers</title>
   <para>
    Rulers appear on the top and the left of the <application>Dia</application>
    canvas.  They show, in centimeters, how large your canvas is.
   </para>
   <para>
    On each ruler exists an arrow.  The arrow moves on the ruler in coordination
    with where the mouse pointer is.  For example, if the user moves the mouse
    up, the vertical ruler's arrow will move up, indicating the change.  These
    arrows become useful when an object needs to line up exactly at a certain
    measurement point.
	</para>
   <para>
    Rulers can be temporarily hidden for the current document by choosing the 
    menu item 
    <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>
      View
     </guimenu>
     <guimenuitem>
      Show Rulers
     </guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
    Rulers, unlike grid lines, cannot be turned off by default for new 
    documents.  
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="background-color">
  <title>Background Colour</title>
   <para>
    The background colour option allows you to change what the background looks
    like in the canvas.  By default, the colour is white.  However, the colour
    can be changed by going into
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>
        View
      </guimenu>
      <guimenu>
        Diagram Properties
      </guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>
        Background
      </guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    and clicking on the bar.  The bar displays the current background colour. 
    The gridlines will change their color automatically to stay visible if
    the background color is changed to black.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="zooming">
  <title>Zooming</title>
   <para>
    Zooming allows the user to get up closer to their diagram.  This helps to
    let the user make precision drawings.
   </para>
   <para>
    The canvas can be zoomed up to 400%.  Zoom can be done by clicking on the
    magnifying glass on the toolbox and clicking on the canvas.  To zoom out,
    hold the shift button and click again on the canvas.
   </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: "dia.xml"
End:
-->
