<chapter label="5" id="basic-objects-chapter">
<title>Basic Objects</title>
<sect1 id="basic-objects-introduction">
<title>Basic Objects Introduction</title>
  <para>
   The first, and most common type of object is the basic object.  Basic objects normally are geometric shapes, which can be customized.  <application>Dia</application> offers
the user numerous basic objects.
  </para>
  <sect2 id="text">
  <title>Text</title>
   <para>
    <application>Dia</application> supports the use of text as its own type of
    object.  Text can be placed on the canvas by clicking on the text button on
    the toolbox.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     Text in <application>Dia</application> can use any font available to Gnome.
    </para>
   </note>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="box">
   <title>Box</title>
    <para>
     The boxes in <application>Dia</application> can be customized to be any
     size desired by the user.  The properties available are:
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Corner Rounding - Causes the corners to be rounded instead of hard
        edges.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Draw Background - Keeps the center clear or fills with the background
        color.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="ellipse">
   <title>Ellipse</title>
    <para>
     An ellipse is a shape which has all rounded sides, such as a circle or an
     oval.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="polygon">
   <title>Polygon</title>
    <para>
     A polygon is any closed shape made up of straight lines.  The
     polygon tool, allows the user to draw any shape with all straight lines.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="beziergon">
   <title>Beziergon</title>
    <para>
     A beziergon is similar to the polygon as the user defines the shape.
     However, it differs in that it allows curves to exist in the shape.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="line">
   <title>Line</title> 
    <para>
     A line simply...a line.  <!--fix this wording...it sucks--> Refer to the
     customizing a line section to find more information about a line.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="arc">
   <title>Arc</title>
    <para>
     An arc is a line which has been bent to create a semi-circle shape.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="zigzagline">
   <title>Zigzag Line</title>
    <para>
     A zigzag line is a line which has sharp, 90 degree turns in it.  They hold
     visual similarities to staircases.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="polyline">
   <title>Poly Line</title>
    <para>
     A poly-line is like a zigzagline, but does not necessarily have to have
     90 degree turns to it.  The angles can be customized.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="bezier">
   <title>Bezier Line</title>
    <para>
     A bezier line is a line which has curves in it.  The bezier line tool is
     edited by clicking and dragging the green and orange dots.  The green dots
     customize the size while the orange dots customize the angles at which the
     line curves at.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="image">
   <title>Images</title>
    <para>
     The <application>Dia</application> canvas can have pictures inside of it,
     as well as shapes.
    </para>
    <para>
     To add an image, click on the image button and then add it to the canvas.
     An object that says "Broken Image" will appear.  Double-click to
     open the properties.  Click on "Browse" and select your file.  Click "OK"
     and then the image will be updated accordingly.
    </para>
    <para>Currently the following image formats are supported for inclusion in
      <application>Dia</application> diagrams:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>ANI</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>BMP</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>GIF</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>ICO</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>JPEG</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>PNG</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>PNM</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>RAS</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>SVG</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>TGA</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>TIFF</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>WMF</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>XBM</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>XPM</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
   </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
